<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Meditation | Julia Chou]]></title>
  <link href="http://jpchou.com/blog/categories/meditation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jpchou.com/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-08T19:40:25-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://jpchou.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Julia Chou]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experiences From a 10 Day Silent Meditation Retreat]]></title>
    <link href="http://jpchou.com/blog/2019/01/08/experiences-from-a-10-day-silent-meditation-retreat/"/>
    <updated>2019-01-08T18:58:07-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://jpchou.com/blog/2019/01/08/experiences-from-a-10-day-silent-meditation-retreat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<hr />

<p><img class="center" src="/images/tomales_bay.jpg" width="800" title="Tomales Bay!" ></p>

<p>The latter half of 2018 saw me turn my attention towards focusing on personal development and self-improvement, and as part of these efforts, I began to explore ways to strengthen my emotional intelligence and self-awareness. I had been monitoring my physical fitness and nutrition for a few years, but I realized that I had neglected to pay corresponding attention to my mental and emotional health.</p>

<p>As I read more and more into these topics, I learned that a common pattern among many successful people is their practice of meditation, to which they give credit for drastically improving their quality of life and emotional stability.
I had always thought of meditation as something one practices for spiritual or religious reasons, and I have never particularly identified myself as either of these things. Perhaps I had also retained a Western unfamiliarity with the practice that made the concept seem foreign to me despite the fact that it&rsquo;s something people have been doing for thousands of years. I was intrigued, however, by the notion that if adopted regularly, meditating can improve one&rsquo;s focus, help create emotional balance, and remove distractions. Seemed pragmatic enough.</p>

<p>I learned about a 10 day Vipassana meditation retreat taught by a man named S.N. Goenka in a book called Never Eat Alone, in which the author spoke of his time there as a truly transformative and transcendent experience that changed his whole worldview. He now retreats for 10 days of silent meditation on a yearly basis.
I&rsquo;m a fairly introspective and contemplative person, so spending 10 days sitting around, not talking to anyone, and discovering new ways to become a better person sounded like something that would be completely in my wheelhouse. Seemed like there was much to potentially gain and little to lose.</p>

<p>I found the website for the Vipassana course and learned they offered a session at a location about an hour and a half outside of San Francisco (where I&rsquo;m currently based), so I went ahead and registered. The organization is run on a donation basis, providing courses for free to new students and only accepting contributions from those who have completed the full 10 days. They even helped coordinate a rideshare board, so I didn&rsquo;t have any financial or logistical concerns.</p>

<p>I was completely unsure of what to expect when I signed up for the course. Now, having completed it, I can say that I found the whole thing frustrating, meaningful, ridiculous, funny, and beneficial all at various times. Below are some observations I&rsquo;ve taken away from my time there.</p>

<hr />

<p><br/></p>

<p><b>DAY 0</b></p>

<p>Students were instructed to arrive the day before the first official day of meditation began for orientation. I discovered when I arrived that the course was being held in a rented space that doubled as a Catholic youth summer camp. The organizers did their best to create a neutral space by taping over signs and covering up any indication that this was anything but a place intended for quiet contemplation. I went through the female registration line and was assigned a top bunk in a 12-person cabin. I was also encouraged to turn in my cell phone for safekeeping during the course, but I opted to hold onto it and just keep it turned off in the bottom of my bag the whole time. Students weren&rsquo;t allowed even books to read or journals to write in.</p>

<p>I mingled with a few fellow students before we all began our silence. A good amount of people seemed to be from the Bay Area, though I met a few from states like Florida and New York. Some came with their partners or, in one case, with their family, which was interesting because the whole point of the retreat is to labor under a sense of isolation. A good number of people had already completed this course, but many, like myself, had little to no experience with meditation whatsoever and were just there to challenge themselves and learn what it was about. Most impressive of all to me was the fact that there was at least one (very) pregnant woman.</p>

<p>Overall, there were about 240 students in total, segregated by gender.</p>

<p>During orientation, the deep, croaking voice of S.N. Goenka (who passed away in 2013 but lives on through audio and video recordings in these courses) played through the speakers and instructed us to fully surrender yourself to the practice of Dhamma and Buddhism and to adopt several precepts throughout the next ten days. Five of the precepts forbade you from killing, stealing, lying, engaging in sexual misconduct, or taking any intoxicants. If you were a returning student, you had to adopt three additional precepts instructing you not to eat after noon, wear any sensory decorations such as jewelry, or sleep in high or luxurious beds.</p>

<p>The vows seemed to just be a formality, as we were all in an environment that made it extremely difficult to disobey most of the precepts. I wondered idly, though, whether or not the top bunk in my 12-person cabin could be considered &ldquo;high&rdquo; or &ldquo;luxurious.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Noble Silence officially began at 8:00 pm. I found the term a little grandiose, but effectively it meant the silence of body, speech, and mind, and no communication whatsoever, whether through speech, hand gestures, or eye contact, was permitted between the students. Students were only allowed to converse with teachers or assistants if they had any questions or concerns about the practice or the technique.</p>

<p><b>DAYS 1–2</b></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/meditation_timetable.png" width="500" title="Meditation Timetable" ></p>

<p>Each day started at around 4:00 am and ended at around 9:30 pm. Students spent the majority of the day meditating, with only a few hours set aside for eating and resting. At the end of each day, we would sit and watch a discourse video in which Goenka would explain meditation techniques, answer some frequently asked questions, and share little Zen koans. Then, he would introduce a new progression in our meditation technique to practice the following day.</p>

<p>We started out learning Anapana meditation, which is observing your respiration, paying attention to the way your breath rushing through your nostrils and across your upper lip.</p>

<p>One of my biggest frustrations already was being physically confined to a small space and instructed to not partake in any physical activity beyond simple stretching. At the same time, it was nice to be able to give free rein to my thoughts and my thoughts alone.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m accustomed to living alone in a studio, so it was quite an adjustment for me to share a cabin with 11 other people. It was alarmingly easy to dehumanize people and think of them as nothing but mindless, thoughtless automatons when you can&rsquo;t look at them and you don&rsquo;t even know their names or the sound of their voices. I gave people nicknames based on the names of colleges or tech companies emblazoned on their sweats. When I couldn&rsquo;t empathize with them much at all, it became all the easier for their loud footsteps, snores, coughing, and sneezing to drive me insane.</p>

<p>During the meditation sessions, part of me thought it was a little morbid that we were all listening to recordings of a man who died years ago. But in a way, it&rsquo;s a beautiful thing that his legacy lives on through these courses and still impacts so many people.</p>

<p><b>DAY 3</b></p>

<p>My frustration and irritation grew as I began to berate myself for running off into the woods to sit around and think about myself as if I had no real problems to deal with or no better way to spend my time. I could have been lifting weights, taking online courses, or reading. Instead, I was trapped within the tiny confines of this children&rsquo;s summer camp without a book, a journal, or a phone.</p>

<p>I often found myself practicing the art of sleeping while sitting up rather than that of meditation.</p>

<p>It vaguely crossed my mind how odd it was that I was spending Christmas and New Year&rsquo;s with a large group of strangers in total silence. I wondered what was going on in the outside world, what kind of celebrations people were getting up to, what new political scandals had occurred, and how financial markets were performing. (Not well at all, for that last one).</p>

<p>I might have been crazy, but I thought I caught the occasional whiff of weed around the cabins and the dining hall, which was somehow both surprising and unsurprising.</p>

<p>There were moments of peace and serenity. The scenery was calm, the air was clear, the sun was bright, and the days were beautiful. At night, the stars were just gorgeous, shining with such clarity and brilliance that you would never witness in the city. </p>

<p>Outside of these moments of gratitude, I quickly started to look forward to getting back to my regular life. I started a nightly ritual of mentally incrementing how much progress I had made through the course.</p>

<p>10% done… 20% done… 30% done…</p>

<p><b>DAY 4</b></p>

<p>On the fourth day, we were introduced to the practice of Vipassana meditation. The purpose behind spending the first few days concentrating on your breath was to sharpen your ability to concentrate on the sensations in a small area of the body, and in Vipassana, you then extend that focus to other areas of the body, starting from the top of the head and traveling down to the toes. The purpose of this was to become aware of the sensations in your body, whether that be itching, aching, numbness, coldness, or the feeling of your heart pulsing. Then, you observe them as they are, divesting any sort of positive or negative interpretation of them. As you focus on them, you notice that these sensations are constantly shifting, which illustrates one of the takeaways of the whole meditation experience: everything (whether that be emotions, sensations, life situations) is fluid, impermanent, and in constant flux. If you can recognize that, you can allow yourself to be fully aware of the present moment but also prevent yourself from becoming too fixated on it because you know it&rsquo;s not going to last.</p>

<p>With this practice of self-observation, you come to realize that nothing is inherently good or bad. Your own biases and perceptions are the only things telling you that they are.</p>

<p>(Take my explanations of these concepts with a hefty pinch of salt, as I&rsquo;m sure this meditation boot camp, though intensive, has left many gaps in my understanding).</p>

<p>As much as the organizers insisted that theirs was a secular practice that didn&rsquo;t involve any rites or rituals, Goenka would end each session singing/chanting blessings for peace and goodwill, which did feel slightly ritualistic.</p>

<p><b>DAY 5</b></p>

<p>Some days, students were called up in groups to meet with their teachers, where the teachers would provide pointers and make sure you were practicing the technique properly.</p>

<p>At these times, I answered questions like &ldquo;Do you feel your equanimity growing stronger?&rdquo;</p>

<p>Why, yes, I suppose so.</p>

<p>To the best of my understanding, equanimity means having the ability to sit on a mat for hours on end, back aching, butt-sore, legs numb, and think &ldquo;Eh. This will pass.&rdquo;</p>

<p>It seems that forcing yourself to endure discomfort is a universal way to train your mind and strengthen your resilience to adversity.</p>

<p>I do wonder, though, whether maintaining the same posture for hours and cutting off circulation ever results in any health issues for long-time meditation practitioners.</p>

<p>The passage of time was excruciating and each day seemed interminable. My only source of entertainment was the constant stream of my own internal dialogue, and the inability to record any of my thoughts was the most painful part of the whole process.</p>

<p>It would have been much easier if I were allowed to acknowledge the existence of the hundreds of other people here. Though I don&rsquo;t miss conversing with people when I&rsquo;m actually alone, it was just absurd that we were a group of about 240 people walking around in contrived little bubbles of isolation bumping into each other in the meditation hall, waiting together in line at the dining hall, and going to sleep and waking up together. It would have been such an eerie scene for an unknowing person to stumble upon, this silent community in the woods. </p>

<p>Once, however, one of my cabin-mates asked me in a whisper whether or not I had a pair of shower shoes, and my heart nearly burst with happiness at this moment of human connection.</p>

<p><b>DAY 6</b></p>

<p>Little moments of joy prevailed. Even though the organizers and teachers did their best to maintain an air of solemnity in the meditation hall, and I had difficulty keeping my composure on many occasions. </p>

<p>People were nodding off all over the place. Once, the girl next to me fell asleep, slipped off her meditation bench, and nearly face-planted into the girl in front of her.</p>

<p>Furthermore, it turned out that however diligently Noble Silence was observed, the meditation hall was anything but silent. In fact, it was difficult not to become irritated by all the distracting sounds. One guy kept burping every ten minutes or so and managed to keep that up for days. Multiple people caught colds, so coughing and sneezing abounded. I had a most uncompassionate fear of being infected by someone around me.</p>

<p>The managers overseeing the women were strict about showing proper respect in the hall by not lying down, stretching excessively, or pointing your feet towards the teachers and would come to chastise you if they saw you doing any of the above. Meanwhile, I would occasionally glance over to the men&rsquo;s half of the hall to see some of them sprawled out and actually snoring on their meditation mats.</p>

<p>Once, I saw a man blowing a kiss towards the direction of the women&rsquo;s side of the meditation hall. He was wearing a wedding ring, so presumably, that was for his wife. </p>

<p>&ldquo;How sweet,&rdquo; I thought. &ldquo;But also, how dare he break the rules!&rdquo;</p>

<p>On another occasion, one of the men rushed out of the hall to the bathroom in order to throw up violently, and the whole hall of 240+ people pretended nothing was amiss and just carried on with their meditations.</p>

<p>We were warned that the practice of meditation may bring forth a lot of deep-rooted negative emotions, and this may ostensibly have been a physical manifestation of the eradication of the complexes nestled in the deepest levels of his consciousness. Alternatively, it is also possible that he just ate a bad piece of fruit.</p>

<p><b>DAY 7</b></p>

<p>Unfortunately, on this day I was forced to break my silence when I asked one of the managers if they had any tampons to spare.</p>

<p>I felt I had reached a tipping point. I was about three-quarters of the way through the course, and I tapped an inner reserve of patience and discipline. The cadence of each day was familiar to me now, and I felt I could calmly pass through the rest of my time here.</p>

<p>Watching Goenka speak in his discourse videos was like watching a kindly old grandpa reading you little parables and teaching you how to build character. At this point, I was really buying into his messages of compassion, peace, patience, tolerance, and forgiveness. I mean, who wouldn&rsquo;t? There is so much beauty in the human spirit, so much love in the soul! It was completely worth coming to this retreat in order to experience these uplifting moments of clarity and connection.</p>

<p><b>DAY 8</b></p>

<p>…Only a few more days left of this stupid shit.</p>

<p><b>DAY 9</b></p>

<p>The last few days weren&rsquo;t the smooth sailing I thought they would be. It seemed that the more fixated I was on my liberation, the slower time flowed. I looked forward to Goenka&rsquo;s discourses, as they were the only source of entertainment throughout the entire stay.</p>

<p>After one particular discourse, I sat deep in thought, pondering a parable regarding how one should maintain awareness of Nature&rsquo;s inherent impermanence and thinking of all the times in my life when I became overly attached to a set of circumstances only to become devastated when they were inevitably altered. However, my musings were abruptly interrupted when a girl sitting near me farted. </p>

<p>Are you kidding me with this? All right, now things couldn&rsquo;t change fast enough.</p>

<p>Despite the managers' attempts to maintain order and respect in the meditation hall, there were, sadly, very many farts. Noble Farts, no doubt.</p>

<p>The vegetarian menus they planned frequently featured beans very prominently. They definitely knew what they were doing.</p>

<p>Around this time, I also realized that I had gained the ability to tell how much time had passed during meditation hours based on the degree of numbness in my butt.</p>

<p><b>DAY 10</b></p>

<p>At around 10:00 am on this day, Noble Silence was broken, and students were allowed to engage in Noble Speech.</p>

<p>They arranged this in order to ease the transition back into regular society, but talking in the meditation hall and physical contact were still prohibited.</p>

<p>Goenka had one last lesson to impart before the course ended, and that was to practice sending metta to others around you after each meditation session. This was a way of sending good wishes, love, and happiness to others. After spending so much time in introspection and establishing your own sense of emotional balance, you were then to reflect that back upon those around you.</p>

<p>A huge amount of relief washed over me when I was finally able to witness that these people I had been living in silence with for the past week and a half are actually thinking, feeling, and sensing human beings who are really funny and very kind.</p>

<p>This speaks more to my own preconceived notions and biases, but I was wondering how many people were proponents of the healing powers of spiritual energy and mystical auras. In fact, I did overhear some mention of Reiki and crystals, but most of the people I talked to were not quite that free-thinking. </p>

<p>We discussed the practicalities of adopting the precepts into our ordinary lives (what constitutes sexual misconduct, anyway? Is it improper to have sexual desires? We eventually settled on a broad definition of misconduct as any action that isn&rsquo;t consensual). We learned each other&rsquo;s occupations as accountants, engineers, contractors, and project managers. We shared life stories, traded Instagram handles, speculated about the lives of our teachers outside of these meditation retreats, and joked about the little absurdities we all noticed during our time of silence.</p>

<p>As it turned out, the four teachers who taught this session were a pair of married couples. The two women were a school teacher and principal in the education system in the Bay Area. I was only slightly disappointed to learn that they weren&rsquo;t some higher beings who annually descended from their higher plane of existence in order to teach this course. I believe you&rsquo;re only approached by organizers to teach the course after you&rsquo;ve gone through several iterations both as a student and as a volunteer.</p>

<p>Time began to fly by once they allowed us to speak.</p>

<p><b>DAY 11</b></p>

<p>The organizers set up information booths in the dining hall so students could pick up literature on how to maintain this practice now that they&rsquo;d finished this course. The way they set up these displays with plastic tables and corrugated cardboard tri-fold boards reminded me of my elementary school science fairs.</p>

<p>I picked up a booklet about how to incorporate meditation into your life as a daily habit and a brochure titled &ldquo;The Art of Living: Vipassana Meditation.&rdquo;</p>

<p>In their closing notes, we were all encouraged to join the Vipassana Facebook group and volunteer to serve in future iterations of the course before finally being released to go our own ways.</p>

<hr />

<p><br/></p>

<p>Overall Takeaways</p>

<p>This was a positive experience and I&rsquo;m glad I did this; however, I wouldn&rsquo;t opt to repeat this particular course. I think dedicating 10+ hours a day to meditation is excessive and an inefficient use of my time. </p>

<p>That&rsquo;s not to say I don&rsquo;t believe the technique is incredibly beneficial, however. I do believe that making a daily habit of simply being calm for a little bit will do wonders for reducing stress and anxiety, and I have noticed an increase in my ability to focus on tasks a little more and to identify and eliminate distractions. I&rsquo;m not entirely sure if this is the result of being contained in an environment of total deprivation of any external stimuli for ten days, so I plan to continue meditating to see if this holds up. I suppose I&rsquo;m still waiting on time to tell if this whole experience will work much of a change in me.</p>

<p>Goenka recommended that students meditate two hours each day: one hour in the morning and one hour at night. However, I&rsquo;ll aim for thirty minutes a day for now.</p>

<p>Everybody gets a little something different out of going through even the same experiences, so I&rsquo;m not sure to whom I would recommend this course. You might emerge feeling like you&rsquo;ve just undergone some spiritual metamorphosis, as many have done, or you might come out thinking it&rsquo;s all utter bullshit. However, if any of this sounds intriguing to you in any way, you can check out their website for yourself and explore further.</p>

<p>As for me, I found my time here immersive and valuable, and I plan to continue reading up on Buddhism and other meditation practices on my own. I&rsquo;m looking forward to seeing where this path leads me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
